Everyone, this is Visan from Gaza, and this is the best time to tell you that I am still alive.
It's the 10th of October, 2025, and I am documenting the return of my people again.
These are the holy scenes that they tried to delete when they forced us, when they tortured us
to flee our homes in the north to the south again during the past two months, but they failed.
This is the second return, and I have never seen or heard about a people that returned twice in one year
by the Palestinian people. That's the north. These are my people in the first hours of return,
and that's the south there. The first time, after 15 months of displacement, I was stuck in a car
for 30 hours in a line that is searched by an international forces to return to my city.
But now, after I chose to stay in the Gaza city, I'm documenting the return of my people
without any search, without any line, just free. No one, no one ever must live this.
No one ever must return after being tortured to flee, to be forced to flee, return to the
rebel of the homes, return to the bodies of the loved people, return under the sun, bare feet,
tired, for two years of a genocide. Finally, we are returning. These are the holy scenes.
These are the scenes that they have tried to delete from our memory. These are the scenes
that they've tried to delete from the history after the first return shaked the existence
of Israel. These are the scenes that they tried hard to convince us that they could not be repeated.
My people is returning for the second time with the same spirit. Yes, they know that the whole city
is either damaged or destroyed. Yes, they know that is not the end. Yes, they know that it's not the
return to the stolen lands in 1948. But we are sure that this is exactly what we need to prove that we
will return. The Gazans and no single one must live this. But if we had to, we will live it just as it
must be. Returning, our heads are up and ready for whatever is coming. Returning back. A holy return.
Returning to the city. Returning to the heart. Returning to the city.